<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Events>
 <Event xml:lang="en" id="2019/254B" href="http://www.nyartbeat.com/event/2019/254B">
  <Name>Félix Fénéon “The Anarchist and the Avant-Garde—From Signac to Matisse and Beyond”</Name>
  <Venue href="http://www.nyartbeat.com/venue/AE192502">
    <Name>The Museum of Modern Art</Name>
    <Type>Museum</Type>
    <Address>11 W 53rd St., New York, NY 10019</Address>
    <Phone>212-708-9400</Phone>
    <Fax></Fax>
    <Access>Between 5th Ave. and 6th Ave.  Subway: V/E to 53rd Street</Access>
    <Area areaId="midtown">Midtown</Area>
    <OpeningHour>10:30:00</OpeningHour>
    <ClosingHour>17:30:00</ClosingHour>
    <DaysClosed mon="0" tue="0" wed="0" thu="0" fri="0" sat="0" sun="0" hol="0" />
    <ScheduleDetails>fridays closinghour 20:00</ScheduleDetails>
    <ScheduleNote>Member Early Hours: 9:30 a.m.–10:30 a.m. daily. The Museum is closed on Thanksgiving Day and Christmas Day.</ScheduleNote>
  </Venue>
  <Media>2D: Painting</Media>
  <Media>2D: Drawing</Media>
  <Description><![CDATA[The Museum of Modern Art announces Félix Fénéon: The Anarchist and the Avant-Garde—From Signac to Matisse and Beyond, the first exhibition devoted to the influential French art critic, editor, publisher, dealer, and collector Félix Fénéon (1861–1944). Though largely unknown today and always discreetly behind the scenes in his own era, Fénéon played a key role in the careers of leading artists from Georges Seurat and Paul Signac to Pierre Bonnard and Henri Matisse, each of whom is featured prominently in the exhibition
 
Félix Fénéon: The Anarchist and the Avant-Garde—From Signac to Matisse and Beyond traces Fénéon’s career through approximately 150 works that highlight his initiatives to help artists via his reviews, exhibitions, and acquisitions; his commitment to anarchism; his literary engagements; and his contributions to the recognition of non-Western art. Bringing together a selection of major works that Fénéon admired, championed, and collected, alongside contemporary letters, documents, and photographs, the exhibition underscores the tremendous impact he had on the development of modernism in the late 19th and early 20th centuries.
 ]]></Description>
  <Image src="http://www.nyartbeat.com/media/event/2019/254B-30" width="30" />
  <Image src="http://www.nyartbeat.com/media/event/2019/254B-80" width="80" />
  <Image src="http://www.nyartbeat.com/media/event/2019/254B-170" width="170" />
  <Karma>0</Karma>
  <Price free="0">Adults $25, Seniors $18, Students $14, Children and Members and on Friday 4pm–8pm Free. Film Admission as of September 1, 2011: $12 adults; $10 seniors, 65 years and over with I.D.; $8 full-time students with current I.D. </Price>
  <DateStart>2019-05-22</DateStart>
  <DateEnd>2021-01-02</DateEnd>
  <ScheduleNote></ScheduleNote>
  <DaysBeforeEnd>16</DaysBeforeEnd>
  <PermanentEvent>0</PermanentEvent>
  <Distance>787.85839239299</Distance>
  <Datum>world</Datum>
  <Latitude>40.761072</Latitude>
  <Longitude>-73.977008</Longitude>
 </Event>

 <Event xml:lang="en" id="2020/3BF8" href="http://www.nyartbeat.com/event/2020/3BF8">
  <Name>Donald Judd “Judd”</Name>
  <Venue href="http://www.nyartbeat.com/venue/AE192502">
    <Name>The Museum of Modern Art</Name>
    <Type>Museum</Type>
    <Address>11 W 53rd St., New York, NY 10019</Address>
    <Phone>212-708-9400</Phone>
    <Fax></Fax>
    <Access>Between 5th Ave. and 6th Ave.  Subway: V/E to 53rd Street</Access>
    <Area areaId="midtown">Midtown</Area>
    <OpeningHour>10:30:00</OpeningHour>
    <ClosingHour>17:30:00</ClosingHour>
    <DaysClosed mon="0" tue="0" wed="0" thu="0" fri="0" sat="0" sun="0" hol="0" />
    <ScheduleDetails>fridays closinghour 20:00</ScheduleDetails>
    <ScheduleNote>Member Early Hours: 9:30 a.m.–10:30 a.m. daily. The Museum is closed on Thanksgiving Day and Christmas Day.</ScheduleNote>
  </Venue>
  <Media>2D: Painting</Media>
  <Media>2D: Drawing</Media>
  <Media>3D: Sculpture</Media>
  <Description><![CDATA[The Museum of Modern Art’s exhibition Judd, on view in The Steven and Alexandra Cohen Center for Special Exhibitions in The David and Peggy Rockefeller Building will be the first major US retrospective dedicated to Donald Judd (1928–1994) in over three decades. Presented solely at MoMA, the exhibition will explore the remarkable vision of an artist who revolutionized the history of sculpture, highlighting the full scope of Judd’s career through 70 works in sculpture, painting, and drawing, from public and private collections in the US and abroad.

Organized by Ann Temkin, The Marie-Josée and Henry Kravis Chief Curator of Painting and Sculpture, with Yasmil Raymond, former associate curator; Tamar Margalit, Curatorial Assistant; and Erica Cooke, Research Fellow, Department of Painting and Sculpture.]]></Description>
  <Image src="http://www.nyartbeat.com/media/event/2020/3BF8-30" width="30" />
  <Image src="http://www.nyartbeat.com/media/event/2020/3BF8-80" width="80" />
  <Image src="http://www.nyartbeat.com/media/event/2020/3BF8-170" width="170" />
  <Karma>0.31959</Karma>
  <Price free="0">Adults $25, Seniors $18, Students $14, Children and Members and on Friday 4pm–8pm Free. Film Admission as of September 1, 2011: $12 adults; $10 seniors, 65 years and over with I.D.; $8 full-time students with current I.D. </Price>
  <DateStart>2020-03-01</DateStart>
  <DateEnd>2021-01-09</DateEnd>
  <ScheduleNote></ScheduleNote>
  <DaysBeforeEnd>23</DaysBeforeEnd>
  <PermanentEvent>0</PermanentEvent>
  <Distance>787.85839239299</Distance>
  <Datum>world</Datum>
  <Latitude>40.761072</Latitude>
  <Longitude>-73.977008</Longitude>
 </Event>

 <Event xml:lang="en" id="2020/203C" href="http://www.nyartbeat.com/event/2020/203C">
  <Name>“Degree Zero: Drawing at Midcentury” Exhibition</Name>
  <Venue href="http://www.nyartbeat.com/venue/AE192502">
    <Name>The Museum of Modern Art</Name>
    <Type>Museum</Type>
    <Address>11 W 53rd St., New York, NY 10019</Address>
    <Phone>212-708-9400</Phone>
    <Fax></Fax>
    <Access>Between 5th Ave. and 6th Ave.  Subway: V/E to 53rd Street</Access>
    <Area areaId="midtown">Midtown</Area>
    <OpeningHour>10:30:00</OpeningHour>
    <ClosingHour>17:30:00</ClosingHour>
    <DaysClosed mon="0" tue="0" wed="0" thu="0" fri="0" sat="0" sun="0" hol="0" />
    <ScheduleDetails>fridays closinghour 20:00</ScheduleDetails>
    <ScheduleNote>Member Early Hours: 9:30 a.m.–10:30 a.m. daily. The Museum is closed on Thanksgiving Day and Christmas Day.</ScheduleNote>
  </Venue>
  <Media>2D: Drawing</Media>
  <Description><![CDATA[The Museum of Modern Art announces Degree Zero: Drawing at Midcentury, an exhibition that will showcase approximately 80 drawings made between 1948 and 1961 exclusively from the Museum’s collection. Degree Zero: Drawing at Midcentury will look across movements, geographies, and generations to highlight connections between diverse artists who embraced drawing to forge a new visual language in the aftermath of World War II. Modest, immediate, and direct, drawing—to use a phrase that circulated among artists and writers during these years—was the ideal “degree zero” medium for this “degree zero” moment. Within this impulse common to artists from across the world, drawing took many forms, from the abstract to the figurative, the organic to the hard-edged. Whether in scrawled graffiti or looping calligraphy, featuring reduced geometry or recording movement via mark-making, these works share similar conceptual and material concerns that manifested specifically in the medium.]]></Description>
  <Image src="http://www.nyartbeat.com/media/event/2020/203C-30" width="30" />
  <Image src="http://www.nyartbeat.com/media/event/2020/203C-80" width="80" />
  <Image src="http://www.nyartbeat.com/media/event/2020/203C-170" width="170" />
  <Karma>0</Karma>
  <Price free="0">Adults $25, Seniors $18, Students $14, Children and Members and on Friday 4pm–8pm Free. Film Admission as of September 1, 2011: $12 adults; $10 seniors, 65 years and over with I.D.; $8 full-time students with current I.D. </Price>
  <DateStart>2020-11-01</DateStart>
  <DateEnd>2021-02-06</DateEnd>
  <ScheduleNote></ScheduleNote>
  <DaysBeforeEnd>51</DaysBeforeEnd>
  <PermanentEvent>0</PermanentEvent>
  <Distance>787.85839239299</Distance>
  <Datum>world</Datum>
  <Latitude>40.761072</Latitude>
  <Longitude>-73.977008</Longitude>
 </Event>

 <Event xml:lang="en" id="2020/F9B9" href="http://www.nyartbeat.com/event/2020/F9B9">
  <Name>Betye Saar “Call and Response”</Name>
  <Venue href="http://www.nyartbeat.com/venue/261A502C">
    <Name>The Morgan Library &amp; Museum</Name>
    <Type>Museum</Type>
    <Address>225 Madison Ave., New York, NY 10016</Address>
    <Phone>212-685-0008</Phone>
    <Fax>212-481-3484</Fax>
    <Access>Corner of 36th St.  Subway: 6 to 33rd Street or 4/5/6 and 7 to Grand Central</Access>
    <Area areaId="midtown">Midtown</Area>
    <OpeningHour>10:30:00</OpeningHour>
    <ClosingHour>17:00:00</ClosingHour>
    <DaysClosed mon="1" tue="1" wed="0" thu="0" fri="0" sat="0" sun="0" hol="1" />
    <ScheduleDetails>Free Fridays: 3 - 5 pm. Reservations are required.</ScheduleDetails>
    <ScheduleNote></ScheduleNote>
  </Venue>
  <Media>2D: Drawing</Media>
  <Description><![CDATA[Los Angeles–based artist Betye Saar (b. 1926) emerged in the 1960s as a major voice in American art. Part of a wave of artists, many of them African American, who embraced the medium of assemblage, she is known best for incisive collages and assemblage sculptures that confront and reclaim racist images. The daughter of a seamstress, and a printmaker by training, Saar brings to her work a remarkable sensitivity to materials. Her imagery is drawn from popular culture, family history, and a wide range of spiritual traditions. 

This exhibition, conceived in close consultation with the artist, looks at the relationship between Saar’s finished works and the preliminary annotated sketches she has made in small notebooks throughout her career. In addition, the show will include approximately a dozen of Saar’s travel sketchbooks with more finished drawings and collages—often relating to leitmotifs seen across her oeuvre—which she has made over a lifetime of journeys worldwide. Selections will cover the span of her career, from the late 1960s up through a sculptural installation made specifically for this exhibition.
 
Betye Saar: Call and Response is organized by the Los Angeles County Museum of Art. The exhibition is curated by Carol S. Eliel, Senior Curator of Modern Art at the Los Angeles County Museum of Art. The coordinating curator at the Morgan Library &amp; Museum is Rachel Federman, Associate Curator of Modern and Contemporary Drawings. The exhibition will travel to Nasher Sculpture Center, Dallas (Fall 2021).
 ]]></Description>
  <Image src="http://www.nyartbeat.com/media/event/2020/F9B9-30" width="30" />
  <Image src="http://www.nyartbeat.com/media/event/2020/F9B9-80" width="80" />
  <Image src="http://www.nyartbeat.com/media/event/2020/F9B9-170" width="170" />
  <Karma>0</Karma>
  <Price free="0">Admission: $22 Adults; $14 Seniors (65 and over); $13 Students. Free to children 12 and under.</Price>
  <DateStart>2020-09-12</DateStart>
  <DateEnd>2021-01-31</DateEnd>
  <ScheduleNote></ScheduleNote>
  <DaysBeforeEnd>45</DaysBeforeEnd>
  <PermanentEvent>0</PermanentEvent>
  <Distance>1018.4557994181</Distance>
  <Datum>world</Datum>
  <Latitude>40.749392</Latitude>
  <Longitude>-73.98175</Longitude>
 </Event>

 <Event xml:lang="en" id="2020/5609" href="http://www.nyartbeat.com/event/2020/5609">
  <Name>David Hockney “Drawing from Life”</Name>
  <Venue href="http://www.nyartbeat.com/venue/261A502C">
    <Name>The Morgan Library &amp; Museum</Name>
    <Type>Museum</Type>
    <Address>225 Madison Ave., New York, NY 10016</Address>
    <Phone>212-685-0008</Phone>
    <Fax>212-481-3484</Fax>
    <Access>Corner of 36th St.  Subway: 6 to 33rd Street or 4/5/6 and 7 to Grand Central</Access>
    <Area areaId="midtown">Midtown</Area>
    <OpeningHour>10:30:00</OpeningHour>
    <ClosingHour>17:00:00</ClosingHour>
    <DaysClosed mon="1" tue="1" wed="0" thu="0" fri="0" sat="0" sun="0" hol="1" />
    <ScheduleDetails>Free Fridays: 3 - 5 pm. Reservations are required.</ScheduleDetails>
    <ScheduleNote></ScheduleNote>
  </Venue>
  <Media>2D: Drawing</Media>
  <Description><![CDATA[David Hockney (b. 1937) is one of the most internationally respected and renowned artists alive today. This exhibition will be the first to focus on his portraits on paper and one of very few exhibitions to investigate his drawing practice. Featuring about 100 drawings, the exhibition will trace a trajectory from Hockney’s early works as a student, to his Ingres-like portraits of the 1970s, and his return to the sketchbooks in the early 2000s. The exhibition will be unique in exploring Hockney’s practice on paper through a small group of sitters he has depicted repeatedly over the years: his muse and confidante, the designer Celia Birtwell; his mother; his friend and curator Gregory Evans, master printer Maurice Payne; and the artist himself. Each of these individuals have been important to Hockney. Over time he has rendered them in different forms: pencil, pen and ink, etchings, photocollages, iphone and ipad drawings. In re-visiting these people over decades, Hockney gives us a unique insight into how his practice has evolved over time. 

An exhibition organized by the National Portrait Gallery, London, in collaboration with the artist and the Morgan Library &amp; Museum.

David Hockney: Drawing from Life is made possible by Mr. and Mrs. Robert King Steel and Katharine J. Rayner. Additional support is provided by the Rita Markus Fund for Exhibitions, with assistance from Dian Woodner and David and Tanya Wells.
]]></Description>
  <Image src="http://www.nyartbeat.com/media/event/2020/5609-30" width="30" />
  <Image src="http://www.nyartbeat.com/media/event/2020/5609-80" width="80" />
  <Image src="http://www.nyartbeat.com/media/event/2020/5609-170" width="170" />
  <Karma>0</Karma>
  <Price free="0">Admission: $22 Adults; $14 Seniors (65 and over); $13 Students. Free to children 12 and under.</Price>
  <DateStart>2020-10-02</DateStart>
  <DateEnd>2021-05-30</DateEnd>
  <ScheduleNote></ScheduleNote>
  <DaysBeforeEnd>164</DaysBeforeEnd>
  <PermanentEvent>0</PermanentEvent>
  <Distance>1018.4557994181</Distance>
  <Datum>world</Datum>
  <Latitude>40.749392</Latitude>
  <Longitude>-73.98175</Longitude>
 </Event>

 <Event xml:lang="en" id="2020/C356" href="http://www.nyartbeat.com/event/2020/C356">
  <Name>“Poetry and Patronage: The Laubespine-Villeroy Library Rediscovered” Exhibition</Name>
  <Venue href="http://www.nyartbeat.com/venue/261A502C">
    <Name>The Morgan Library &amp; Museum</Name>
    <Type>Museum</Type>
    <Address>225 Madison Ave., New York, NY 10016</Address>
    <Phone>212-685-0008</Phone>
    <Fax>212-481-3484</Fax>
    <Access>Corner of 36th St.  Subway: 6 to 33rd Street or 4/5/6 and 7 to Grand Central</Access>
    <Area areaId="midtown">Midtown</Area>
    <OpeningHour>10:30:00</OpeningHour>
    <ClosingHour>17:00:00</ClosingHour>
    <DaysClosed mon="1" tue="1" wed="0" thu="0" fri="0" sat="0" sun="0" hol="1" />
    <ScheduleDetails>Free Fridays: 3 - 5 pm. Reservations are required.</ScheduleDetails>
    <ScheduleNote></ScheduleNote>
  </Venue>
  <Media>3D: Installation</Media>
  <Description><![CDATA[Young, handsome, and highborn, Claude III de Laubespine lived in luxury after marrying an heiress and obtaining the favor of King Charles IX. His brilliant career at court was cut short in 1570, when he died at the age of 25. He left behind a splendid library, which was dispersed, and only recently have his books been identified and properly appreciated for their superb quality and fine bindings. Laubespine now ranks among the great collectors of the French Renaissance.

For the first time in more than 400 years, this exhibition brings together some of the most spectacular bindings in that collection, exquisite examples of Renaissance ornamental design. They will be shown along with related artwork and literary memorials of Laubespine. He left his books to his sister, a patron of the poet Pierre de Ronsard, who praised her country estate, the library, and its perfumed bindings, which, he said, “smells as good as your orange trees.” This exhibition will evoke the sensual pleasure and literary connoisseurship implicit in a noble library of that era.]]></Description>
  <Image src="http://www.nyartbeat.com/media/event/2020/C356-30" width="30" />
  <Image src="http://www.nyartbeat.com/media/event/2020/C356-80" width="80" />
  <Image src="http://www.nyartbeat.com/media/event/2020/C356-170" width="170" />
  <Karma>0</Karma>
  <Price free="0">Admission: $22 Adults; $14 Seniors (65 and over); $13 Students. Free to children 12 and under.</Price>
  <DateStart>2020-10-16</DateStart>
  <DateEnd>2021-05-16</DateEnd>
  <ScheduleNote></ScheduleNote>
  <DaysBeforeEnd>150</DaysBeforeEnd>
  <PermanentEvent>0</PermanentEvent>
  <Distance>1018.4557994181</Distance>
  <Datum>world</Datum>
  <Latitude>40.749392</Latitude>
  <Longitude>-73.98175</Longitude>
 </Event>

 <Event xml:lang="en" id="2020/DF5F" href="http://www.nyartbeat.com/event/2020/DF5F">
  <Name>Edmund Burke “Sublime on the Small Scale”</Name>
  <Venue href="http://www.nyartbeat.com/venue/261A502C">
    <Name>The Morgan Library &amp; Museum</Name>
    <Type>Museum</Type>
    <Address>225 Madison Ave., New York, NY 10016</Address>
    <Phone>212-685-0008</Phone>
    <Fax>212-481-3484</Fax>
    <Access>Corner of 36th St.  Subway: 6 to 33rd Street or 4/5/6 and 7 to Grand Central</Access>
    <Area areaId="midtown">Midtown</Area>
    <OpeningHour>10:30:00</OpeningHour>
    <ClosingHour>17:00:00</ClosingHour>
    <DaysClosed mon="1" tue="1" wed="0" thu="0" fri="0" sat="0" sun="0" hol="1" />
    <ScheduleDetails>Free Fridays: 3 - 5 pm. Reservations are required.</ScheduleDetails>
    <ScheduleNote></ScheduleNote>
  </Venue>
  <Media>2D: Painting</Media>
  <Media>2D: Drawing</Media>
  <Description><![CDATA[In 1757, the British statesman and philosopher Edmund Burke published A Philosophical Enquiry into the Origin of Our Ideas of the Sublime and Beautiful, an aesthetic treatise that profoundly influenced artists across Europe well into the nineteenth century. Burke understood the Sublime as deriving from “whatever is fitted in any sort to excite the ideas of pain, and danger, that is to say, whatever is in any sort terrible…or operates in a manner analogous to terror.” He emphasized the powerful, even pleasurable, emotional response that could arise from the contemplation of such possibilities, particularly when considered from a place of safety.

Many artists turned to the natural world as their principal source of the Sublime, emphasizing its magnitude and power. While the Sublime is mostly associated with large-scale oil paintings intended to engulf and overwhelm viewers, artists frequently worked on a smaller scale to develop and experiment with their representations. They endeavored to render nature and its effects faithfully by sketching en plein air, particularly on their travels through dramatic landscapes. The oil sketches displayed here engage with a range of Sublime effects, from the impressive vastness of a mountain range and the thrill of rushing water to the terror of a raging storm.

Sublime on the Small Scale highlights works from the collection of oil sketches given jointly to the Morgan and the Metropolitan Museum of Art by Trustee Eugene V. Thaw.

]]></Description>
  <Image src="http://www.nyartbeat.com/media/event/2020/DF5F-30" width="30" />
  <Image src="http://www.nyartbeat.com/media/event/2020/DF5F-80" width="80" />
  <Image src="http://www.nyartbeat.com/media/event/2020/DF5F-170" width="170" />
  <Karma>0</Karma>
  <Price free="0">Admission: $22 Adults; $14 Seniors (65 and over); $13 Students. Free to children 12 and under.</Price>
  <DateStart>2020-09-29</DateStart>
  <DateEnd>2021-09-12</DateEnd>
  <ScheduleNote></ScheduleNote>
  <DaysBeforeEnd>269</DaysBeforeEnd>
  <PermanentEvent>0</PermanentEvent>
  <Distance>1018.4557994181</Distance>
  <Datum>world</Datum>
  <Latitude>40.749392</Latitude>
  <Longitude>-73.98175</Longitude>
 </Event>

 <Event xml:lang="en" id="2020/57DA" href="http://www.nyartbeat.com/event/2020/57DA">
  <Name>Shahzia Sikander “Weeping Willows, Liquid Tongues”</Name>
  <Venue href="http://www.nyartbeat.com/venue/EEDD4AC1">
    <Name>Sean Kelly Gallery</Name>
    <Type>Gallery</Type>
    <Address>475 10th Ave., New York, NY 10018 </Address>
    <Phone>212-239-1181</Phone>
    <Fax>212-239-2467</Fax>
    <Access>Between 36th and 37th Sts. Subway: A/C/E to Penn Station 34th Street</Access>
    <Area areaId="midtown">Midtown</Area>
    <OpeningHour>11:00:00</OpeningHour>
    <ClosingHour>18:00:00</ClosingHour>
    <DaysClosed mon="1" tue="0" wed="0" thu="0" fri="0" sat="0" sun="1" hol="0" />
    <ScheduleDetails></ScheduleDetails>
    <ScheduleNote>saturdays openinghour 10:00, saturdays closinghour 18:00</ScheduleNote>
  </Venue>
  <Media>2D: Painting</Media>
  <Media>2D: Drawing</Media>
  <Media>3D: Sculpture</Media>
  <Description><![CDATA[Sean Kelly presents Shahzia Sikander’s inaugural exhibition with the gallery and her first exhibition in New York City in nine years. Weeping Willows, Liquid Tongues is an expansive, in-depth look into Sikander’s recent work, featuring the artist’s dynamic large-and-intimately-scaled drawings, a captivating new single channel video-animation, luminous, intricate mosaics and her first ever free-standing sculpture.

Shahzia Sikander takes classical Indo-Persian miniature painting as the point of departure for her work. From premodern beginnings to contemporary influences, it is precisely this historical continuum and its continuous capacity for reinvention that has sparked Sikander’s visually rich engagement in multiple media. The works in the exhibition explore tensions between power and powerlessness to present transformative ideas. Sikander’s interest in sociology, psychoanalysis, and the examination of how culture and society shape the imagination is all fodder for her work. The ways in which violence, systemic racism, class and cultural fears are deeply entrenched in media and political representations, be it the fear of the unknown, the migrant, the immigrant, the Muslim, the LGBTQ community, the ‘other’ and the various fault lines of race, class and gender also intersect within her work. In this tangled web, the extractive nature of capitalism appears to promise liberty and happiness, but too often bestows debt and despair. These ideas are all explored in her new series of paintings The Shroud, 2020 and Oil and Poppies, 2020, which emerged whilst the artist was researching symbols of extraction.

Sikander’s first major sculptural work, Promiscuous Intimacies, borrows its title from Gayatri Gopinath’s forthcoming essay on Sikander’s practice. This bronze sculpture, with its sinuous entanglement of a Greco-Roman Venus and an Indian Devata, explores in Gopinath’s words, “the promiscuous intimacies of multiple times, spaces, art historical traditions, bodies, desires, and subjectivities.” In their suggestive embrace, the intertwined female bodies bear the symbolic weight of communal identities from multiple geographic terrains. They evoke non-heteronormative desires that are often cast as foreign and inauthentic, and instead challenge the viewer to imagine a different present and future. The backward glance of the lower figure “demands that we understand ‘tradition,’ ‘culture,’ and ‘identity’ as impure, heterogenous, unstable, and always in process,” disrupting “taken-for-granted national, temporal, and art historical boundaries.”  

Presenting a comprehensive overview of Sikander’s films, the exhibition will feature three animations: Parallax, 2013, Disruption as Rapture, 2016, and her most recent film, Reckoning, 2020. The new film, made from multiple drawings, reveals the cyclical theme of struggle through kinetic forms. In it, Sikander considers the relationships between migrant-citizen, conflict-erosion, memory-myth, warfare-fatality, father-son, and human - nature. The musical score accompanying Reckoning is written by the inimitable composer Du Yun, awarded the Pulitzer in Music in 2017, and features the Pakistani singer Zeb Bangash. Du Yun and Sikander’s decade-long collaborations (including Parallax and Disruption as Rapture) span Shanghai, New York, Sharjah, Istanbul, Hong Kong and Pakistan and speak to their ‘creative intimacy,’ female agency and shared passion for finding common ground through multiple languages.

While questioning the very concept of national culture, Sikander provides deep aesthetic reflections on the history of colonialism, capitalism and the formation of racialized identities in the present. Our ecological condition is a mirror of social conditions: erosion of climate, borders, rising waters, rising heat, and displacement of bodies amongst others. All resources are gathered in the rubric of monetization: language, labor, human intelligence and human attention. Sikander reimagines the United States’ foundational claims of freedom and liberty, that were never applicable to all, by presenting overlapping diasporas and using art to imagine the possibilities of a more just and livable future. Sikander’s work is not about hybridity. It is not fusing cultures or aesthetics. The multiple juxtapositions reflecting gender, race, class, and language differences are arranged and rearranged to imagine visual forms that challenge fixed narratives and break binary thinking in all its forms. Sikander’s work is the antithesis of the fictions of purity and authentic national culture.

Sikander lives and works in New York City. Her innovative artistic practice led to her meteoric rise internationally in the mid-nineties with survey exhibitions at the Renaissance Society at the University of Chicago, 1998, the Kemper Museum of Contemporary Art 1998, the Hirshhorn Museum and Sculpture Garden 1999, and the Whitney Museum of American Art 2000. Sikander has had major solo exhibitions throughout the world, including most recently at the Asian Art Museum, San Francisco, 2017; the Aga Khan Museum, Toronto, 2017; MAXXI | Museo nazionale delle arti del XXI secolo, Rome 2016; the Asia Society Hong Kong Center, Hong Kong, 2016; the Guggenheim Museum, Bilbao 2015; the Smithsonian American Art Museum, Washington D.C. 2012; the Museum of Contemporary Art, Tokyo, 2010; the Irish Museum of Modern Art, Dublin, 2007; the Museum of Contemporary Art, Sydney, 2007; the Pérez Art Museum Miami, 2005; and at the San Diego Museum of Art, California, 2004 amongst others. Sikander has been invited to participate in significant international biennials such as the Lahore Biennale 01, Pakistan; the Karachi Biennale 17, Pakistan; the 6th Moscow Biennale of Contemporary Art, Manege, Russia; the 8th and 13th Istanbul Biennial, Turkey;  the 5th Auckland Triennial, New Zealand; the Sharjah Biennale 11, Sharjah Art Foundation, UAE; the 54th and 51st International Art Exhibition of La Biennale di Venezia, Italy; and The Whitney Biennial, New York amongst others. In addition, she has been included in notable group exhibitions at institutions such as the National Museum of Modern and Contemporary Art, Seoul; Martin-Gropius-Bau, Berlin; the Museum of Modern Art, New York. Amongst the numerous awards, grants, and fellowships Sikander has received are the KB17 Karachi Biennale Shahneela and Farhan Faruqui Popular Choice Art Prize, 2017; the Religion and the Arts Award, 2016; the Asia Society Award for Significant Contribution to Contemporary Art, 2015; the National Medal of Arts Award presented by U.S. Secretary of State, Hillary Rodham Clinton, 2012; the John D. and Catherine T MacArthur Foundation Achievement ‘Genius’ award, 2006; and Tamgha-e-Imtiaz, the National Pride of Honor Award presented by the Pakistani Government.

Shahzia Sikander will be the subject of a traveling exhibition titled Shahzia Sikander: Extraordinary Realities. The exhibition will open at The Morgan Library, New York in June 2021 followed by the RISD Museum, Rhode Island in November 2021, and MFA Houston, Texas in Spring 2022. On the occasion of these exhibitions, there will be a major new monograph printed. Extraordinary Realities, is an exhaustive examination of Sikander’s work from 1987 to 2003, charting her early development as an artist in Lahore and the United States, and foregrounding her critical role in bringing miniature painting into dialogue with contemporary art. Edited by Jan Howard and Sadia Abbas, with contributions by Gayatri Gopinath, Faisal Devji, Kishwar Rizvi, Sadia Abbas, Jan Howard, Vasif Kortun, Dennis Congdon, Bashir Ahmed, Rick Lowe and Julie Mehretu.]]></Description>
  <Image src="http://www.nyartbeat.com/media/event/2020/57DA-30" width="30" />
  <Image src="http://www.nyartbeat.com/media/event/2020/57DA-80" width="80" />
  <Image src="http://www.nyartbeat.com/media/event/2020/57DA-170" width="170" />
  <Karma>0</Karma>
  <Price free="1">Free</Price>
  <DateStart>2020-11-05</DateStart>
  <DateEnd>2020-12-19</DateEnd>
  <ScheduleNote></ScheduleNote>
  <DaysBeforeEnd>2</DaysBeforeEnd>
  <PermanentEvent>0</PermanentEvent>
  <Distance>1083.7312668556</Distance>
  <Datum>world</Datum>
  <Latitude>40.756241</Latitude>
  <Longitude>-73.998131</Longitude>
 </Event>

 <Event xml:lang="en" id="2020/376E" href="http://www.nyartbeat.com/event/2020/376E">
  <Name>Beth Lipman “Collective Elegy”</Name>
  <Venue href="http://www.nyartbeat.com/venue/EB18574C">
    <Name>Museum of Arts &amp; Design</Name>
    <Type>Museum</Type>
    <Address>2 Columbus Circle, New York, NY 10019</Address>
    <Phone>212-299-7777</Phone>
    <Fax></Fax>
    <Access>At 58th St. and 8th Ave.  Subway: B/C/D to 59th Street/Columbus Circle</Access>
    <Area areaId="midtown">Midtown</Area>
    <OpeningHour>11:00:00</OpeningHour>
    <ClosingHour>18:00:00</ClosingHour>
    <DaysClosed mon="1" tue="0" wed="0" thu="0" fri="0" sat="0" sun="0" hol="1" />
    <ScheduleDetails>thursdays closinghour 21:00</ScheduleDetails>
    <ScheduleNote>In the Summer opened on Tuesdays.  Check with the venue for details.</ScheduleNote>
  </Venue>
  <Media>2D: Photography</Media>
  <Media>3D: Sculpture</Media>
  <Media>3D: Installation</Media>
  <Media>3D: Ceramics</Media>
  <Media>Screen: Video installation</Media>
  <Description><![CDATA[The Museum of Arts and Design (MAD) presents Beth Lipman: Collective Elegy, a major midcareer survey that is the first to assess the remarkable achievements of the renowned contemporary artist. From sumptuous displays of excess, including provocative installations comprising hundreds of individual glass elements, to poetic and contemplative works in glass, metal, clay, video, and photography, the works on view are ethereal meditations on time and mortality and simultaneously sobering indictments of our contemporary consumer culture and its impact on the planet.

“For more than twenty years, Beth has built on the still-life tradition, illustrating the ability of objects to signify wealth, class, and identity. She further critiques Western society’s capitalist values and the environmental consequences of unfettered consumption,” said Samantha De Tillio, MAD’s curator of collections. “A new project, House Album, investigates the subjectivity of history and the necessity of including a wider range of voices in its telling; a topic of particular importance in 2020.”

Lipman’s monumental Laid (Time-) Table with Cycads forms the centerpiece of the exhibition. Melding landscape and tablescape through representations of prehistoric plant life bursting forth through a table laden with goblets, bowls of fruit, books, textiles, and other cultural markers, the work evokes the interdependence and tension between humanity and the natural world.

“Collective Elegy represents a decade of investigation centering the human condition, demarcating the present moment in deep time,” said Lipman. “In this sense, the work examines aspects of material culture and history through still lifes, site-specific installations, and photographs.”

Accompanying the exhibition is an 88-page catalog, published by the Museum and Lucia | Marquand, featuring full-color plates of Lipman’s artworks, to be released in early 2021. Public programs and workshops to be scheduled during the run of the exhibition will illuminate the exhibition’s content and themes further and will encourage participants to explore and consider the materiality of glass.

Beth Lipman: Collective Elegy is curated by MAD’s curator of collections, Samantha De Tillio.

Born in Philadelphia, Beth Lipman is a multidisciplinary sculptor living and working in Wisconsin. She earned her Bachelor of Fine Arts from Tyler School of Art, Temple University in 1994. Lipman has received numerous awards including the USA Berman Bloch Fellowship, Pollock Krasner Grant, and a Louis Comfort Tiffany Foundation Grant and was recently inducted into the American Craft Council’s College of Fellows. Lipman’s work has been widely exhibited at institutions such as Ringling Museum of Art, Sarasota, FL; ICA/MECA, Portland, ME; RISD Museum, Providence, RI; Milwaukee Art Museum, WI and Gustavsbergs Konsthall, Gustavsberg, Sweden. Lipman’s work is in the collection of over 30 museums, including the Smithsonian American Art Museum, Washington, D.C.; North Carolina Museum of Art, Raleigh, NC; Des Moines Art Center, IA; Brooklyn Museum of Art, NY; Kemper Museum for Contemporary Art, Kansas City, MO; and the Jewish Museum, New York, NY.]]></Description>
  <Image src="http://www.nyartbeat.com/media/event/2020/376E-30" width="30" />
  <Image src="http://www.nyartbeat.com/media/event/2020/376E-80" width="80" />
  <Image src="http://www.nyartbeat.com/media/event/2020/376E-170" width="170" />
  <Karma>0</Karma>
  <Price free="0">Adults $15, Students and Seniors $12, Members and Children under 12 Free, Thursdays 6 - 9pm Pay What You Wish</Price>
  <DateStart>2020-09-25</DateStart>
  <DateEnd>2021-04-04</DateEnd>
  <ScheduleNote></ScheduleNote>
  <DaysBeforeEnd>108</DaysBeforeEnd>
  <PermanentEvent>0</PermanentEvent>
  <Distance>1093.9735354251</Distance>
  <Datum>world</Datum>
  <Latitude>40.767589</Latitude>
  <Longitude>-73.982067</Longitude>
 </Event>

 <Event xml:lang="en" id="2020/E0CD" href="http://www.nyartbeat.com/event/2020/E0CD">
  <Name>Robert Mangold Exhibition</Name>
  <Venue href="http://www.nyartbeat.com/venue/0D35F0FE">
    <Name>Pace Prints Gallery</Name>
    <Type>Gallery</Type>
    <Address>32 E 57th St., 3 Fl., New York, NY 10022</Address>
    <Phone>212-421-3237</Phone>
    <Fax>212-832-5162</Fax>
    <Access>Corner of Madison Ave.  Subway: F to 57th Street, 4/5/6 to 59th Street/Lexington Avenue, N/R/W to 5th Avenue</Access>
    <Area areaId="midtown">Midtown</Area>
    <OpeningHour>09:30:00</OpeningHour>
    <ClosingHour>17:30:00</ClosingHour>
    <DaysClosed mon="1" tue="0" wed="0" thu="0" fri="0" sat="0" sun="1" hol="0" />
    <ScheduleDetails>saturdays openinghour 10:00, saturdays closinghour 17:00</ScheduleDetails>
    <ScheduleNote></ScheduleNote>
  </Venue>
  <Media>2D: Prints</Media>
  <Description><![CDATA[Pace Prints presents an exhibition which spans nearly fifty years of printmaking by Robert Mangold. Many of the editions on view were created by Mangold since 1993 in Pace Prints’ printshops. In addition, the artist selected prints from 1973 to 2010 that will elaborate on the breadth of his printmaking career. Historically, Mangold has used color as a structural element and this exhibition highlights monochromatic works from early screenprints to recent color aquatints published by Pace Prints. 

This exhibition runs concurrently with Robert Mangold: Paintings 2017-2019, on view at Pace Gallery (540 West 25th Street) through November 14. 

Robert Mangold’s practice has commonly been to create drawings first, followed by printmaking and painting. Occasionally the prints and drawings will evolve simultaneously. This process allows the artist to elaborate on ideas put forth in a drawing (or series of drawings) in different media. In the 1970s, the artist often used screenprinting to share his images. Experimentation with other printmaking techniques led Mangold to focus on etchings and woodcuts from the 1980s forward. A drypoint etched line could shift from fine to textured, mimicking graphite. Woodblocks and aquatint etchings both offered subtle gradation in color and shifts in texture within the images. Mangold came to enjoy the woodcut process so much, he hand-carved woodblocks annually to create small prints as gifts to friends.

In addition to a selection of the thirty-one etchings and woodcuts created by Robert Mangold with Pace Prints since 1993, this exhibition will feature five screenprints from the 1970s, two from the 1980s, and five etchings from the 1990s. The five aquatints with etchings entitled The Attic Series II (VI-X), 1990-91, are an iconic set of five polygonal shapes in rich, saturated color. Each if the five asymmetrical images have an interior black line, that appears to push out toward the edge of the shape. Mangold has often created prints in a series, which can be seen throughout this exhibition.]]></Description>
  <Image src="http://www.nyartbeat.com/media/event/2020/E0CD-30" width="30" />
  <Image src="http://www.nyartbeat.com/media/event/2020/E0CD-80" width="80" />
  <Image src="http://www.nyartbeat.com/media/event/2020/E0CD-170" width="170" />
  <Karma>0</Karma>
  <Price free="1">Free</Price>
  <DateStart>2020-11-05</DateStart>
  <DateEnd>2020-12-18</DateEnd>
  <ScheduleNote></ScheduleNote>
  <DaysBeforeEnd>1</DaysBeforeEnd>
  <PermanentEvent>0</PermanentEvent>
  <Distance>1212.7284958963</Distance>
  <Datum>world</Datum>
  <Latitude>40.762472</Latitude>
  <Longitude>-73.972308</Longitude>
 </Event>

</Events>